HDFC Life Sanchay PLUS
Something is wrong with it
Let's change it
Now, it is better
[Sanchay MINUS]
Calculate Premium -
Something is wrong with it also
Yes, it is better
[CALCULATE LOSS]
Namaskar Friends,
[Intro Music]
Guys Welcome back to the channel
I am money-minded MANDEEP
I am going to tell you a ninja technique
You can burn your money
yourself using that technique
The core plan is the same
But companies have launched
different versions with different names
You can find these plans in
every life insurance company
For Example, Endowment Plan
Even customers have to check the
meaning of this word using dictionary
Companies decided to keep a name
which can attract more customers
That's why they came with names like
GUARANTEED MATURITY
Then Guaranteed Life-Long Income,
Double Income, Money Back Plan
Sanchay MINUS, or
Assured Wealth Plan
In which, everything is assured expect wealth
believe me
Seriously, India is facing two main problems
No. 1,   Agents get high commissions up
to 25% when they sell these plans
So, they have a good
motivation to sell these plans
But that doesn't mean
those plans are good for you
If the Relationship Managers of banks fail
to sell these plans and achieve their target
Then they are mistreated and
they don't get incentives
The second problem is the lack
of awareness among customers
When someone uses words like
Guaranteed income or double income
Then people are ready to invest
their money without further research
Many people even feel proud after buying these
products that he/she is responsible for family
But you have done nothing for your
family if you have bought any such plan
You are not alone if you have any such plan
My father also has a such plan
He has an endowment policy
continued form 2009
I was not aware at that time
as I was in 9th class
There was no such awareness
on Youtube also as it is today
So, I can't blame my father but I can share
some shocking truth of that policy with you
We have to face a loss of 1 lakh
because we discontinued that policy
So, should I discontinue it with facing
a 1 lakh loss or should I continue?
So, my point is clear. I am 100%
against these policies
But I will explain all facts transparently
Then we will discuss something which
will be very important for YOUR future
But first of all, Let's understand what is
Endowment Plan, Money Back Plan
Guaranteed Income, Double Income, etc etc
These all plans are sold by
an insurance company to you
That's why you will definitely get
a life insurance component in these plans
They have made a combo by
adding Investment component
Like Cold Coffee + Icecream
This is Insurance + Investment
How this is deffernet then ULIP?
I told you in the ULIP video that
your investment is market-linked
This means you will get returns based
on the performance of that fund
But here the amount you
will get is pre-decided
As its name says Guaranteed
Income, Double Income
You know from day 1 that
what you will get on maturity
The agent will also add two other points here -
No 1, this is tax-free income
No 2, this is guaranteed income
But you will also get annual
bonus declared by the company
That's why your amount will be
greater than guaranteed income
Let's clear all points one by one
First of all, let's discuss
Life Insurance Component
As I have told you many times,
While taking a life insurance
You have to ask one question to yourself
How much amount my family
needs if I die tomorrow?
This amount should be a minimum 10
times of your annual income after tax
You must have a minimum of 1 crore life
cover if you earn 10 lakh annually
It can be a maximum of up to 25 crore (25X)
Depending on the premium you can afford
But a person must have a minimum of 1 crore
life cover if he earns 10 lakh annually
So that his family can maintain the same
life style for the next 10 years if he dies today
Family need not worry about
school fees or other expenses
Let me show you the life cover which
you get in these endowment plans
And the premium which you pay for these plans
HDFC Life Sanchay Plus Plan
is here which is quite famous
But this should be MINUS in the place of PLUS
Minimum premium is 30,000
but let me type 50,000
If I click on VIEW BENEFITS
then this indicates that
My sum assured is 6.5 lakh if I pay
50,000 Rupees premium annually
This is not a life cover
The company is doing this favor for me
What will we do with this great amount??
Point no 1, If I need a 1 crore life insurance
cover then this is no where close to that amount
Point no 2, this insurance is very expensive
if you are 25 years old and you need
1 crore insurance cover in TERM PLAN
Then you have to pay only
10-12,000 Rupees annual premium
This premium is 5X greater than that
There is a little modification
They are saying that
I will get 12.5 lakh if I die at the age of 44
And I will get 6.5 lakh if I die early
How can someone decide
that when will he/she die?
The reason behind increment in maturity cover with
age is not that they are increasing your life cover
This is increasing because this is a combo
plan which also includes investment
So, the amount which your family will
get depends upon the age you die
This is my father's endowment plan of MAX LIFE
Its annual premium is 20 thousand rupees
But its cover is only 2.14 lakh rupees
This is not a life cover but a favor
which company is doing with us
If you are thinking that why life
insurance is so expensive in these plans
Its answer is  -  GREED
As the IRDA Guidelines, companies have to
pay a minimum 10X cover of annual premium
The company will give a cover of 2-3 lakh
if the company is charging 20,000 premium
But maximum cover in their hands
So, they will not give enough cover
even after charging a high premium
The conclusion of the insurance component
can be explained in only one word  -  CHHEE
Now, let's discuss the investment
component of Endowment Plan
Let's take an example of
Max Life Guaranteed Income Plan
As their illustration, if someone pays
a premium of 1 lakh till 12 years
Then he will get 1.31 lakh from the 13th year
He will get 2.62 lakh from the 18th year
(Double of Previous)
In the last year(21nd Year), he will get a
2.62 lakh and 2 lakh rupees additionally
You invested 12 lakh rupees and you are
getting a return of 21.70 Lakh till maturity
Two points are noticeable here
One - the amount is fixed here
You already know that how much
you will get in 13th year or 17th year
And secondly, your money will be doubled
People love the feeling of doubling the money
But you should think about the rate of return
You should know the rate by which your
money is growing in any investment
You have to calculate Internal
Rate Of Return (IRR)
We have to use EXCEL to calculating IRR
I have entered -1 Lakh for the years 1 to 12
Because I am paying 1 lakh every year
I have entered +1.31 Lakh in my 13th year
I have entered 2.62 Lakh 18th year onwards
In the last year (22nd year), I have entered
2.62 Lakh + 2 Lakh as mentioned in the plan
Now, we will use a formula
I will write = IRR
And will enter the first cell and the last cell
The first cell is D2 and the last cell is D23
You will be surprised as you will enter this formula
Because you will know that your money
will grow with a rate of only 5% in this plan
Even FD is better than this
which has not any Lock-In
I will disclose the truth of surrender
value if you close this plan in the middle
This is a joke with the name INVESTMENT
Let's see another plan
HDFC Sanchay MINUS
There are 4 options in Sanchay MINUS
Guaranteed Maturity, Guaranteed Income,
Life-Long Income etc
You can check the IRR of
these plans to know the truth
Let me calculate it for the
Guaranteed Maturity Plan
You have to pay a 1 lakh annual
premium for the first 10 years
I have entered -1 Lakh for the first 10
years as I am paying this amount
I will get nothing from the year 11th to 19th
That's why I have entered 0 here
I will get 22.72 Lakh rupees in the
20th year. So, I entered the same
I again used the IRR Formula
And this money is growing with
an annual rate of only 6%
Let us discuss Max Life Assured Wealth Plan
If you pay 1 lakh premium
each year for the first 5 years
You will get 7.51 Lakh in the 10th year
This money is also growing with the rate of 6%
There are some plans in which your
money grows with the rate of 4.4%, 4.8%
BTW, this Max Life Plan is known as
ASSURED WEALTH PLAN
They have transformed the meaning of the name
wealth by stating a 7.5 lakh amount as wealth
As this logic, This is neither a good
insurance plan nor a good investment plan
Some people may think that
this investment is tax-free
We will get a deduction in 80C
Its returns are also tax-free
If your return is already very low and
you also have to pay a tax on it
Then people will not buy this product
Secondly, this investment is
considered under the debt category
You get indexation benefit in debt
investment if you hold more than 3 years
We have explained in this video
You can watch for more details
If your money has grown with such a
pathetic rate that it even can't beat inflation
Then your payable tax will be zero
after implementing indexation benefit
So, if your return doesn't beat inflation
then anyway you will not pay the tax
If it is about Section 80C, then watch
this video to know about all benefits
Let's see surrender and lock-in in my father's policy
Its annual premium is 20,000 Rupees
We are paying it for the last 10 years
This means we have already paid
the premium of 2 Lakh rupees
I will get only 85K Rupees
if I surrender it today
It means I have to face a loss of 1.15 Lakh
I have to bear the loss of half of my own
money because I can't wait till maturity
Some people may attract towards
bonuses of these policies
Let me reveal the black truth of bonuses
Suppose you took a 20 years policy
Suppose bonus was declared in 10th year
But you can't get that bonus in
your bank account on that day
That bonus will be in your policy and you
will get it on maturity after 10 more years
So, if you even get a 5-10K Bonus than
you can't touch it for the next 10 years
You may think that you will get a return on this
money or this will be invested somewhere
Your 5K bonus declared in the 10th year will be
same 5K in the 20th year when you will get it
The power of that money would have
been decreased due to inflation
So, you are not creating wealth.
You are destroying it on purpose
People even feel proud after
investing in such policies
They feel proud because they
took a life cover for their family
Secondly, they think that they are investing also
They feel responsible after securing
their family's future in such a way
This thought is being planted in your mind
by showing these emotional pictures
They are conveying a message that these
people are happy because they took this policy
You are not doing right
by buying these products
When free education is available on YouTube
Then you won't have anyone
else to blame but yourself
If you realize in the future that you
have done nothing for your family
Let me tell you the exact loss
After 10 years of taking the policy, if
you realize that we have done wrong
You are ready to invest 1 lakh rupees
in such plans (Means 8.5K Per month)
Let's consider the monthly investment of 8,000 rupees
Monthly Investment - 8,000 Rupees
Rate of Return - 12%
12% is expected with a good mutual fund
You can do it 11 or 10 if you disagree
I am doing SIP for 10 years
You will invest around 9.5 Lakh in 10 years
You will get 18.5 lakh rupees
Means you doubled your amount in 10 years
You get the same amount in
these plans after 20-22 years
You are in an 18.5 Lakh loss if you are
invested in these plans for only 10 years
Let me keep this 18.5 Lakh amount as it is
I will not invest it further
I will keep it as it is for the next 20 years
The amount will be near 1.80 Crore
Your total investment duration was 10 years
You invested only in starting 10 years
You didn't invest for the rest of 20 years
Still, your amount will be 1.80 Crore
If you have invested in any
endowment plan for 10 years
And then you realize that you have done wrong
then you can't create such a big amount now
Because you have less time now
And you can't invest more now
As you have responsibilities as house
expenses, the study of children, etc
You have lost crores if you lost 10
years because TIME IS MONEY
I am discontinuing my father's
policy because TIME IS MONEY
I am doing it even after I
have to bear a loss of 1.15 LAKH
As I have already lost the opportunity
of investing money for 10 years
Now, I don't want to lose it
for further 10-15 years
That amount can grow rapidly
if I invest it in a good option
I still have my future's 10-15 years
I will not take any life or term insurance
for my father after closing it
As I have already told you many times that
Term insurance is useful for the
people who have dependents
But I am a single child of my parents
and I am self-dependent
It means no one is dependent on my parents
so they don't need a term insurance
I can invest the amount which I
would have paid in term insurance
That's why I always advise you to
think that what you actually need
If there is any dependent on you
and you need a life insurance
Then you should go with term insurance
which is the best insurance product
Secondly, you are becoming old with time
If you want to take a term plan after 10
years then your premium will be high
Final question - What should you
do if you don't buy these plans
The process is simple. Your
priority should be family's security
Your family should get enough
money if you die today
So, your priority should be to take
term insurance for yourself
Because it is the cheapest
life insurance in the world
You can get a 1-1.5 Crore cover by
paying a Rs 10-15K annual premium
Then you need health insurance
As diseases don't come with an invitation
Our lifestyle has changed a lot
and hospitals bills are very expensive
So, we need financial help at that time
Then your priority should be
to have an emergency fund
So, you can get a financial
support if you lose your job
You should have a separate fund which should
have money equal to your 6 months salary
You just need to keep that money
You can do an FD or put it in a liquid fund
Then you should prefer diversified investing
Always prefer diversified investing and don't
hesitate to pay money to professionals for it
Invest your money in various options like
stocks, mutual funds, Debt, NPS, etc
But your some portion of the money
should be invested in stocks
Some people disagreed in the last video
that how can I expect a 12% return
This can be less or more than 12
You have a 0% chances of earning
20% return if you don't invest
If you have done diversified investment then you
don't need to worry if you get only a 7-8% return
As your entire money was not invested in
that option. You have diversified your portfolio.
That's why you should invest some
money in stocks and mutual funds
I am giving you the link of 2
discount brokers in description
One is ZERODHA and another is UPSTOX
Both are India's best broker in my opinion
In fact you have to pay 0%
brokerage on equity delivery
You can indirectly support us if you
open Demat account using our link
You can open an account within 24 hours
The entire process is paperless
You should buy 1-2 shares after opening
your account using your savings
Because you will learn better
when you will invest yourself
Free knowledge is available
on YouTube so use that
Officially video is completed and you can go now
But I have to talk with you about a serious point
and I would appreciate it if you will listen
An agent comes to you. Most probably
he is your close friend or a relative
He sells you such plan and
you blindly trust on him
Ideally, you should trust as he
is your close friend/relative
But you should understand that
it is his job and he will sell plans
This is not always true that
he always wants to loot you
The sad reality is that being an insurance
agent in this country is very easy
There is a 1-hour exam and you can easily clear it
At the time of these fresher's training
They get specific instructions that
Don't sell term plan because
the commission is very less
So, they lie that term plans
are useless for customers
That's why they teach them to sell
Endowment, ULIP, Money-Back, etc
Because the commission is high in these plans
These words are not mine. This is the
real-life experience of an insurance agent
Who commented about this and
he left his job after 4 months
This means if your relative comes to
you as an agent to sell these plans
It doesn't mean that he wants to loot you
but he doesn't know the reality of these plans
That's why he choose these plans
also for himself and his family
I request you that don't trust
blindly on anyone including me
You should verify all the information
which I have told you today
Learn to calculate returns, read about
finance, research about it
Always ask good questions to the
people on whom you trust
That's why I am always thankful to the people
who comment their doubts and criticize
I also include their comments in the video
I don't want that LLA should be a
channel on which people trust blindly
Don't trust blindly. Learn from
here but do your own research.
Let's meet in a new video
Let's connect on Instagram
Thanks for watching,,,,,By